<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: jQuery | RyLand]]></title>
  <link href="http://ryalnd.github.com/blog/categories/jquery/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ryalnd.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-11T20:10:10-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ryalnd.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[ryland]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Site, New Job]]></title>
    <link href="http://ryalnd.github.com/blog/2011/03/15/new-site-new-job/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-15T07:48:21-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ryalnd.github.com/blog/2011/03/15/new-site-new-job</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been a few weeks since I last posted.  Quite a bit's happened in that time.</p>

<p>To begin, I finally found a job.  Starting Wednesday I'll be working a regular 9-to-5, doing primarily technical support for pharmacy software.  While it's only a temporary position and doesn't involve much development, I'm still really looking forward to some structure and a more 'normal' circadian rhythm.  I consider myself one of those people that loves to work, and get genuine satisfaction from doing a job well.  Also, it's well-paying and I'm dead broke; that certainly doesn't hamper my anticipation.</p>

<p>I haven't done any Project Euler since I reached Level 2.  I felt it was a good stopping point for the time being, but I've definitely learned a lot from it and plan on doing a problem or two when the urge strikes; perhaps in a new language.  It's been really good for learning syntax and structure basics for Python, and at this point I feel confident that I could pretty easily solve most problems with it.  If you're looking to learn a new language, applications (in the literal sense) to math problems are in my opinion a great way to start.</p>

<p>Still working on a couple of web development contracts, both for starting businesses.  They're going well, although the biggest problem I'm having is with the level of detail to which I'm giving these sites.  I'm trying to keep things quick and simple, but jQuery and PHP make doing all these awesome things so simple that I end up spending wayyy too much time experimenting with features the client neither asked for nor particularly needs.  Giving them more than they asked for up-front isn't really a problem in itself (deleting is pretty simple), but it's becoming one given that these need to get finished post-haste since time will be sparse come tomorrow.</p>

<p>Finally, I launched a site last week called (tentatively): <a href="http://lucy-dog.com">Lucy In Hats</a>.  It started out as a joking comment about my girlfriend's dog, and within a few hours I had bought a domain name and had something up and running.  I've been making tweaks and adding features since then, but the concept's been the same since the start: people vote on pictures of an adorable mini-pug in silly hats.</p>

<p>I ended up going through with the idea because I wanted to see how much traffic I could generate to the site, under the general knowledge that people can't get enough of cute animals.  That and learning the underlying technologies needed for a relatively simple site like this were my main goals for the project. The fact I only had to spend $10 on a domain name got things off the ground right away.</p>

<p>I've done some 'advertising' on Facebook, both on my account and on the lady's; beyond that I've been relying on word-of-mouth and people's attraction to cuteness.  I'd say he site is a success even at this point, at least as compared to ry-land.com and this blog.</p>

<p>As of right now I've had around 10x as many unique visitors to the site as to ry-land.com, and about 35x as many page views.  Granted, I haven't advertised ry-land.com on Facebook, nor is there dynamic content to drive all those page views, but I'm still pretty impressed by its popularity in the first week.</p>

<p>I'm really cranking out the jQuery and PHP and doing new stuff with them every day.  I'm enjoying it, learning a bunch, and tomorrow I should even start making some money again.  Not bad.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
