<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: backbone | Ryland Herrick]]></title>
  <link href="http://rylnd.github.com/blog/categories/backbone/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rylnd.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-06T16:35:47-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://rylnd.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ryland Herrick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Still Alive!]]></title>
    <link href="http://rylnd.github.com/blog/2013/06/20/still-alive/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-20T00:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rylnd.github.com/blog/2013/06/20/still-alive</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>I was doing some style work on the blog recently, and I remembered that no one will care how good the site looks if there&rsquo;s no content. I know I&rsquo;ve not posted in a while, as my main outlets have been either <a href="http://twitter.com/rylnd">twitter</a> or <a href="https://coderwall.com/rylnd">coderwall</a>, so please check those out if there&rsquo;s nothing new here. Links are at the bottom, as well.</p></blockquote>

<p>I installed the wonderful <a href="https://github.com/tlvince/leanpress">leanpress</a> theme for this site, which as you&rsquo;ll remember is run on Octopress. I had to make a few customizations (mostly to fix up some gross old posts), but I&rsquo;m really loving its minimalism and emphasis on readability.</p>

<p>I think I&rsquo;m getting familiar enough with design that I&rsquo;ve reached a refinement phase, where the emphasis shifts from learning <em>how</em> to do something to learning <em>when</em> to do it. I no longer want a blog that&rsquo;s technologically impressive, I want one that people can read.</p>

<p>At almost two years into my career in web development, the most useful skill I&rsquo;ve acquired, without a doubt, is git. The concepts of source control combined with the power and prevalence of git make for a near-universally marketable skill. I love it and have a lot of thoughts on the topic, but I&rsquo;m saving them for another blog post.</p>

<p>At the beginning of my career, I didn&rsquo;t even know enough to recognize that big source-control-sized hole in my skillset. What was glaringly obvious, though, was that I didn&rsquo;t know javascript. However, since November I&rsquo;ve been working on an impressively large Backbone.js project with a team of awesome developers. Needless to say, I feel like I&rsquo;ve climbed that mountain as well. At the very least, I know what I don&rsquo;t know, but I feel confident in saying that I &lsquo;get&rsquo; javascript, now.</p>

<p>Of course, I owe it all to <a href="http://bendyworks.com">Bendyworks</a>. They saw my potential and enthusiasm, and gave me a strong foundation and the freedom to seek out my passions. In return, I&rsquo;ve done my best to help grow Bendyworks into the finest company that I can imagine.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
