<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hackathon | RyLand]]></title>
  <link href="http://ryalnd.github.com/blog/categories/hackathon/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ryalnd.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-11T22:05:40-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://ryalnd.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[ryland]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Much More Exciting(er)]]></title>
    <link href="http://ryalnd.github.com/blog/2011/05/25/much-more-excitinger/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-25T17:49:12-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ryalnd.github.com/blog/2011/05/25/much-more-excitinger</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Oh snap.  Lots of exciting stuff happening lately.  Most publicly, I finally got some old code up on <a href="https://github.com/ryalnd">GitHub</a> a week or so ago.  'Social Coding' is such an amazingly cool concept, I deeply regret not participating sooner.  I literally get giddy when I load my dashboard.  It's probably love.  Follow me or just lurk; I'll be posting some more projects in the near future, and probably talking about it here.</p>

<p>In an exciting new development, Spreenkler has apparently changed their minds about the whole Zappos Gift Certificate thing (thanks to a rogue email by Devin, of which I swear I had no knowledge).  We've yet to receive the goods, but Steve @ <a href="http://www.spreenkler.com/">Spreenkler</a> apparently talked to the guys at Blurbs and they agreed that we could have the award.  I was dumbfounded by the kindness exhibited in that gesture; if Steve and co. are representative of the Milwaukee community, I cannot wait.</p>

<p>Going along with that, I may have been offered an amazing opportunity for the summer that could really help kick-start things for me.  I'll give more details when things are more definite, but in the meantime I hope you're as excited as I am.</p>

<p>In other news, I finally checked my site out in IE today and it was HORRIBLE.  I'm more generally of the stance 'F*** IE users' but the overwhelming numbers and my inability to ignore a problem once it's noticed led me to fix things up.</p>

<p>I have so much stuff I want to read, code, and watch.  There aren't enough hours in the day. 'night for now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
