<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: meetup | Ryland Herrick]]></title>
  <link href="http://rylnd.github.com/blog/categories/meetup/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rylnd.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-16T04:24:06-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://rylnd.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ryland Herrick]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quick Post]]></title>
    <link href="http://rylnd.github.com/blog/2011/05/25/quick-post/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-25T17:23:36-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://rylnd.github.com/blog/2011/05/25/quick-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First: I started this post on Monday, but never got around to finishing it.</p>

<p>Went to the Mad Railers meetup Monday, despite my body requesting otherwise.  I figure if I don&rsquo;t have the time to sit down and learn Ruby right myself right now, I should at least take advantage of these local groups.</p>

<p>The topic was testing, and while that might not be where most people would start when learning a new language (myself included), I have no doubts that it will help me in the long run.  There were a few great talks and I learned quite a bit.  I&rsquo;m slowly putting the framework together in my mind, piece by piece.</p>

<p>My general approach to learning practical programming has been &lsquo;abstraction is a treat that must be deserved.&rsquo;  While higher-level languages are amazing and I absolutely cannot wait to use them professionally, at the same time I feel like I need to program a little &lsquo;lower&rsquo; for a while to appreciate and understand things to a reasonable degree.  Subsequently a good deal of what I do has holes and certainly isn&rsquo;t as comprehensive as if I&rsquo;d put the same amount of work on top of a template.  But finding and plugging those holes is a great learning experience.</p>

<p>Running my own VPS and web server has probably been the best project, education-wise.  There are certainly plenty of holes and configurations that go into system administration stuff, along with being great practice with bash.  I didn&rsquo;t really get that when I was a student, but I&rsquo;m sure glad I&rsquo;m doing it now.</p>

<p>Knowledge is power.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
